<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<dhammapada>
  <chapter chapter="1">
    <title pali="Yamaka 1 Vagga" en="The Twin Verses" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="1">Mind is the forerunner of (all evil) states.  Mind is chief; mind-made are they. If one speaks or acts with an unwholesome mind, because of that, suffering follows one, even as the wheel follows the hoof of the draught-ox.</par>
      <summary>Evil begets evil</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="2">Mind is the forerunner of (all good) states. Mind is chief; mind-made are they. If one speaks or acts with a wholesome mind, because of that, happiness follows one, even as one's shadow that never leaves. </par>
      <summary>Good begets good</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="3">"He abused me, he beat me, he defeated me, he robbed me", in those who harbour such thoughts hatred is not appeased.</par>
      <par nr="4">"He abused me, he beat me, he defeated me, he robbed me", in those who do not harbour such thoughts hatred is appeased. </par>
      <summary>Retaliation does not lead to peace</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="5">Hatreds is never overcome by hatred in this world; hatred is only overcome by love . This is an eternal law. </par>
      <summary>Anger is conquered by love</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="6">The others  know not that in this quarrel we perish;  those of them who realize it, have their quarrels calmed thereby. </par>
      <summary>Quarrels cease through right thinking</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="7">Whoever lives contemplating pleasant things,  with senses unrestrained, in food immoderate, indolent, inactive, him verily Mara  overthrows, as the wind (overthrows) a weak tree.</par>
      <par nr="8">Whoever lives contemplating "the Impurities",  with senses restrained, in food moderate, full of faith,  full of sustained energy, him Mara overthrows not, as the wind (does not overthrow) a rocky mountain. </par>
      <summary>The weak succumb to temptation but not the strong</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="9">Whoever, unstainless, without self control and truthfulness, should don the yellow robe,  is not worthy of it.</par>
      <par nr="10">He who is purged of all stain, is well-established in morals and endowed with self-control and truthfulness, is indeed worthy of the yellow robe.</par>
      <summary>The pure are worthy of the yellow robe but not the impure</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="11">In the unessential they imagine the essential , in the essential they see the unessential - they who entertain (such) wrong thoughts  never realize the essence.</par>
      <par nr="12">What is essential they regard as essential, what is unessential they regard as unessential - they who entertain (such) right thoughts  realize the essence.</par>
      <summary>Right perception leads to the realization of the truth</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="13">Even as rain penetrates as ill-thatched house, so does lust penetrate an undeveloped mind.</par>
      <par nr="14">Even as rain does not penetrate a well-thatched house, so does lust not penetrate a well-developed  mind.</par>
      <summary>Lust pierces the hearts of the undeveloped but not those of the developed</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="15">Here he grieves,  hereafter he grieves.  In both states the evil-doer grieves. He grieves, he is afflicted, perceiving the impurity of his own deeds.</par>
      <summary>Evil-doers suffer here and hereafter</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="16">Here he rejoices,  hereafter he rejoices.  In both states the well-doer rejoices. He rejoices, exceedingly rejoices, perceiving the purity of his own deeds. </par>
      <summary>Happy are the well-doers here and hereafter</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="17">Here he suffers, hereafter he suffers. In both states the evil-doer suffers. "Evil have I done" (thinking thus), he suffers. Furthermore, he suffers, having gone to a woeful state. </par>
      <summary>The evil-doer laments here and hereafter</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="18">Here he is happy, hereafter he is happy. In both states the well-doer is happy. "Good have I done" (thinking thus), he is happy. Furthermore, he is happy, having gone to a blissful state.</par>
      <summary>Happy are the righteous</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="19">Though much he recites the Sacred Texts,  but acts not accordingly, that heedless man is like a cowherd who counts others' kine. He has no share in the fruits  of the Holy Life. </par>
      <par nr="20">Though little he recites the Sacred Texts, but acts in accordance with the teaching, forsaking lust, hatred and ignorance, truly knowing, with mind well freed, clinging to naught here and hereafter, he shares the fruits of the Holy Life.</par>
      <summary>Learning without practice is of no worth</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="2">
    <title pali="Appamada Vagga" en="Heedfulness" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="21">Heedfulness  is the path to the deathless,  heedlessness is the path to death. The heedful do not die;  the heedless are like unto the dead.</par>
      <par nr="22">Distinctly understanding this (difference ), the wise (intent) on heedfulness rejoice in heedfulness, delighting in the realm of the Ariyas. </par>
      <par nr="23">The constantly meditative,  the ever steadfast ones realize the bond-free,  supreme Nibbana. </par>
      <summary>The heedless die; the heedful do not</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="24">The glory of him who is energetic, mindful, pure in deed, considerate, self-controlled, right-living, and heedful steadily increases.</par>
      <summary>The energetic prosper</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="25">By sustained effort, earnestness, discipline, and self-control let the wise man make for himself an island,  which no flood overwhelms.</par>
      <summary>By their efforts the wise create their own heavens</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="26">The ignorant, foolish folk indulge in heedlessness; the wise man guards earnestness as the greatest treasure.</par>
      <par nr="27">Indulge not in heedlessness; have no intimacy with sensuous delights. Verily, the earnest, meditative person obtains abundant bliss.</par>
      <summary>Be heedful not heedless</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="28">When an understanding one discards heedlessness by heedfulness, he, free from sorrow, ascends to the palace of wisdom and surveys the sorrowing folk as a wise mountaineer surveys the ignorant groundlings. </par>
      <summary>Heedlessness should be conquered by heedfulness</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="29">Heedful amongst the heedless, wide awake amongst the slumbering, the wise man advances as does a swift horse, leaving a weak jade behind.</par>
      <summary>The strenuous and the alert overtake the thoughtless and the indolent</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="30">By earnestness Maghava  rose to the lordship of the gods.  Earnestness is ever praised; negligence is ever despised.</par>
      <summary>Earnestness leads to sovereignty</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="31">The Bhikkhu  who delights in heedfulness, and looks with fear on heedlessness, advances like fire, burning all fetters  great and small.</par>
      <summary>The heedful advance</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="32">The Bhikkhu who delights in heedfulness, and looks with fear on heedlessness, is not liable to fall.  He is in the presence of Nibbana.</par>
      <summary>The heedful are in the presence of nibbana</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="3">
    <title pali="Citta Vagga" en="Mind" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="33">The flickering, fickle mind,  difficult to guard, difficult to control - the wise person straightens it as a fletcher straightens an arrow.</par>
      <par nr="34">Like a fish that is drawn from its watery abode and thrown upon land, even so does this mind flutter. Hence should the realm of the passions be shunned. </par>
      <summary>Straighten your fickle mind</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <summary>Control your mind</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="36">The mind is very hard to perceive, extremely subtle, flits wherever it listeth. Let the wise person guard it; a guarded mind is conducive to happiness.</par>
      <summary>Guard your thoughts</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="37">Faring far, wandering alone,  bodiless,  lying in a cave,  is the mind. Those who subdue it are freed from the bond of Mara.</par>
      <summary>Free are they who have controlled their minds</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="38">He whose mind is not steadfast, he who knows not the true doctrine, he whose confidence wavers - the wisdom  of such a one will never be perfect.</par>
      <par nr="39">He whose mind is not soaked (by lust) he who is not affected (by hatred), he who has transcended both good and evil  - for such a vigilant  one there is no fear.</par>
      <summary>To the vigilant there is no fear</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="40">Realizing that this body is (as fragile) as a jar, establishing this mind (as firm) as a (fortified) city he should attack Mara  with the weapon of wisdom. He should guard his conquest  and be without attachment. </par>
      <summary>Fortify your mind and be non-attached</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="41">Before long, alas! this body will lie upon the ground, cast aside, devoid of consciousness, even as a useless charred log. </par>
      <summary>Without the mind the body is useless</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="42">Whatever (harm) a foe may do to a foe, or a hater to a hater, an ill-directed mind  can do one far greater (harm).</par>
      <summary>An ill-disposed mind is the greatest enemy</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="43">What neither mother, nor father, nor any other relative can do, a well-directed mind  does and thereby elevates one.</par>
      <summary>A well-directed mind is far greater than even a mother or a father</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="4">
    <title pali="Puppha Vagga" en="Flowers" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="44">Who will comprehend  this earth (self ), and this realm of Yama,  and this world  together with the devas?  Who will investigate the well taught Path of Virtue , even as an expert (garland maker) will pick flowers?</par>
      <par nr="45">A disciple in training (sekha ), will comprehend this earth, and this realm of Yama together with the realm of the devas. A disciple in training will investigate the well-taught Path of Virtue even as an expert (garland-maker) will pick flowers.</par>
      <summary>The noble disciple will conquer this self</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="46">Knowing that this body is like foam,  and comprehending its mirage-nature,  one should destroy the flower-shafts of sensual passions (Mara), and pass beyond the sight of the king of death. </par>
      <summary>Like a mirage is this body</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="47">The man who gathers flowers (of sensual pleasure), whose mind is distracted, death carries off as a great flood sweeps away a sleeping village.</par>
      <summary>Death takes the sensual unawares</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="48">The man who gathers flowers (of sensual pleasure), whose mind is distracted, and who is insatiate in desires, the Destroyer  brings under his sway.</par>
      <summary>With ungratified desires the sensual die</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="49">As a bee without harming the flower, its colour or scent, flies away, collecting only the honey, even so should the sage wander in the village. </par>
      <summary>Saintly monks cause no inconvenience to any</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="50">Let not one seek others' faults, things left done and undone by others, but one's own deeds done and undone.</par>
      <summary>Seek not others' faults but your own</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="51">As a flower that is lovely and beautiful but is scentless, even so fruitless is the well-spoken word of one who does not practise it.</par>
      <par nr="52">As a flower that is lovely, beautiful, and scent-laden, even so fruitful is the well-spoken word of one who practises it.</par>
      <summary>Practice is better than mere teaching</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="53">As from a heap of flowers many a garland is made, even so many good deeds should be done by one born a mortal.</par>
      <summary>Do much good</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="54">The perfume of flowers blows not against the wind, nor does the fragrance of sandalwood, tagara  and jasmine but the fragrance of the virtuous blows against the wind; the virtuous man pervades every direction.</par>
      <par nr="55">Sandalwood, tagara, lotus, jasmine: above all these kinds of fragrance, the perfume of virtue is by far the best.</par>
      <summary>Moral fragrance wafts everywhere</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="56">Of little account is the fragrance of tagara or sandal; the fragrance of the virtuous, which blows even amongst the gods, is supreme.</par>
      <summary>The scent of virtue is by far the best</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="57">Mara  finds not the path of those who are virtuous, careful in living, and freed by right knowledge.</par>
      <summary>Rebirth-consciousness of arahants cannot be traced</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="58">As upon a heap of rubbish thrown on the highway, a sweet-smelling lovely lotus may grow, even so amongst worthless beings, a disciple of the Fully Enlightened One outshines the blind worldlings in wisdom. </par>
      <par nr="59">As upon a heap of rubbish thrown on the highway, a sweet-smelling lovely lotus may grow, even so amongst worthless beings, a disciple of the Fully Enlightened One outshines the blind worldlings in wisdom. </par>
      <summary>Greatness may be found even amongst the basest the wise outshine worldlings</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="5">
    <title pali="Bala Vagga" en="Fools" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="60">Long is the night to the wakeful; long is the league to the weary; long is samsara  to the foolish who know not the Sublime Truth.</par>
      <summary>Long is samsara to those who know not the dhamma</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="61">If, as the disciple fares along, he meets no companion who is better or equal, let him firmly pursue his solitary career. There is no fellowship  with the foolish. </par>
      <summary>Avoid companionship with the foolish</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="62">"Sons have I; wealth have I": Thus is the fool worried. Verily, he himself is not his own. Whence sons? Whence wealth?</par>
      <summary>One is not one's own</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="63">The fool who knows that he is a fool is for that very reason a wise man; the fool who thinks that he is wise is called a fool indeed.</par>
      <summary>Wise is he who acknowledges his foolishness</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="64">Though a fool, through all his life, associates with a wise man, he no more understands the Dhamma than a spoon (tastes) the flavour of soup.</par>
      <summary>A fool cannot appreciate the value of the dhamma</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="65">Though an intelligent person, associates with a wise man for only a moment, he quickly understands the Dhamma as the tongue (tastes) the flavour of soup.</par>
      <summary>The wise can appreciate the value of the dhamma</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="66">Fools of little wit move about with the very self as their own foe, doing evil deeds the fruit of which is bitter.</par>
      <summary>Bitter is the fruit of evil</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="67">That deed is not well done when, after having done it, one repents, and when weeping, with tearful face, one reaps the fruit thereof.</par>
      <summary>Not well done is that deed which causes repentance</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="68">That deed is well done when, after having done it, one repents not, and when, with joy and pleasure, one reaps the fruit thereof.</par>
      <summary>Well done is that deed which causes no repentance</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="69">As sweet as honey is an evil deed, so thinks the fool so long as it ripens not; but when it ripens, then he comes to grief.</par>
      <summary>Evil-doers come to grief</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="70">Month after month a fool may eat only as much food as can be picked up on the tip of a kusa grass blade;  but he is not worth a sixteenth part of them who have comprehended the Truth. </par>
      <summary>Realization is far superior to mere fasting</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="71">Verily, an evil deed committed does not immediately bear fruit, just as milk curdles not at once; smouldering, it follows the fool like fire covered with ashes.</par>
      <summary>Evil takes effect at the opportune moment</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="72">To his ruin, indeed, the fool gains knowledge and fame; they destroy his bright lot and cleave his head. </par>
      <summary>Knowledge and fame tend to the ruin of fools</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="73">The fool will desire undue reputation, precedence among monks, authority in the monasteries, honour among other families.</par>
      <par nr="74">Let both laymen and monks think, "by myself was this done; in every work, great or small, let them refer to me". Such is the ambition of the fool; his desires and pride increase.</par>
      <summary>The ignorant seek undue fame</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="75">Surely the path that leads to worldly gain is one, and the path that leads to Nibbana is another; understanding this, the bhikkhu, the disciple of the Buddha, should not rejoice in worldly favours, but cultivate detachment. </par>
      <summary>The path to gain is one and to nibbana is another</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="6">
    <title pali="Pandita Vagga" en="The Wise" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="76">Should one see a wise man, who, like a revealer of treasure, points out faults and reproves; let one associate with such a wise person; it will be better, not worse, for him who associates with such a one.</par>
      <summary>Associate with the wise who try to correct you</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="77">Let him advise, instruct, and dissuade one from evil; truly pleasing is he to the good, displeasing is he to the bad.</par>
      <summary>Advisers are pleasing to the good, but not to the bad</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="78">Associate not with evil friends, associate not with mean men; associate with good friends, associate with noble men.</par>
      <summary>Cultivate good friendship</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="79">He who imbibes the Dhamma abides in happiness with mind pacified; the wise man ever delights in the Dhamma revealed by the Ariyas. </par>
      <summary>Happily he lives who drinks of the dhamma</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="80">Irrigators lead the waters; fletchers bend the shafts; carpenters bend the wood; the wise control themselves.</par>
      <summary>The wise control themselves</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="81">As a solid rock is not shaken by the wind, even so the wise are not ruffled by praise or blame.</par>
      <summary>Unshaken as a rock are the wise amidst praise and blame</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="82">Just as a deep lake is clear and still, even so, on hearing the teachings, the wise become exceedingly peaceful. </par>
      <summary>The wise are peaceful</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="83">The good give up (attachment for) everything;  the saintly prattle not with sensual craving: whether affected by happiness or by pain, the wise show neither elation nor depression.</par>
      <summary>The wise are neither elated nor depressed</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="84">Neither for the sake of oneself nor for the sake of another (does a wise person do any wrong); he should not desire son, wealth or kingdom (by doing wrong): by unjust means he should not seek his own success. Then (only) such a one is indeed virtuous, wise and righteous.</par>
      <summary>Success should not be sought by wrongful means</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="85">Few are there amongst men who go Beyond; the rest of mankind only run about on the bank. </par>
      <par nr="86">But those who act rightly according to the teaching, which is well expounded, those are they who will reach the Beyond - Nibbana - (crossing) the realm of passions,  so hard to cross.</par>
      <summary>Few go beyond</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="87">Coming from home to the homeless, the wise man should abandon dark states  and cultivate the bright. He should seek great delight in detachment (Nibbana), so hard to enjoy. Giving up sensual pleasures, with no impediments,  the wise man should cleanse himself of the impurities of the mind.</par>
      <par nr="88">Coming from home to the homeless, the wise man should abandon dark states  and cultivate the bright. He should seek great delight in detachment (Nibbana), so hard to enjoy. Giving up sensual pleasures, with no impediments,  the wise man should cleanse himself of the impurities of the mind.</par>
      <par nr="89">Whose minds are well perfected in the Factors of Enlightenment,  who, without clinging, delight in "the giving up of grasping"  (i.e., Nibbana), they, the corruption-free, shining ones, have attained Nibbana even in this world.</par>
      <summary>Give up evil, cultivate good</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="7">
    <title pali="Arahanta Vagga 1" en="The Worthy" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="90">For him who has completed the journey,  for him who is sorrowless, for him who from everything  is wholly free,  for him who has destroyed all Ties,  the fever (of passion) exists not. </par>
      <summary>No suffering for the emancipated</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="91">The mindful exert themselves. To no abode are they attached. Like swans that quit their pools, home after home they abandon (and go). </par>
      <summary>Arahants are free from attachment</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="92">They for whom there is no accumulation,  who reflect well over their food,  who have Deliverance  which is Void and Signless, as their object - their course, like that of birds in the air, cannot be traced.</par>
      <summary>Be not attached to food</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="93">He whose corruptions are destroyed, he who is not attached to food, he who has Deliverance, which is Void and Signless, as his object - his path, like that of birds in the air, cannot be traced.</par>
      <summary>Free are the undefiled ones</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="94">He whose senses are subdued, like steeds well-trained by a charioteer, he whose pride is destroyed and is free from the corruptions - such a steadfast one even the gods hold dear.</par>
      <summary>The sense-controlled are dear to all</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="95">Like the earth a balanced and well-disciplined person resents not. He is comparable to an Indakhila.  Like a pool unsullied by mud, is he; to such a balanced one  life's wanderings do not arise. </par>
      <summary>Like the earth arahants resent not</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="96">Calm is his mind, calm is his speech, calm is his action, who, rightly knowing, is wholly freed,  perfectly peaceful,  and equipoised.</par>
      <summary>Calm are the peaceful</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="97">The man who is not credulous,  who understands the Uncreate  (Nibbana), who has cut off the links,  who has put an end to occasion  (of good and evil), who has eschewed  all desires,  he indeed, is a supreme man.</par>
      <summary>Noble is he who is not credulous</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="98">Whether in village or in forest in vale or on hill,  wherever Arahants dwell - delightful, indeed, is that spot.</par>
      <summary>Delightful is the spot where arahants dwell</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="99">Delightful are the forests where worldlings delight not; the passionless  will rejoice (therein), (for) they seek no sensual pleasures.</par>
      <summary>Delightful are the forests to the passionless</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="8">
    <title pali="Sahassa Vagga" en="Thousands" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="100">Better than a thousand utterances, comprising useless words, is one single beneficial word, by hearing which one is pacified.</par>
      <summary>One useful sentence is better than a thousand useless words</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="101">Better than a thousand verses, comprising useless words, is one beneficial single line, by hearing which one is pacified.</par>
      <summary>One useful verse is better than a thousand useless verses</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="102">Should one recite a hundred verses, comprising useless words, better is one single word of the Dhamma, by hearing which one is pacified.</par>
      <par nr="103">Though one should conquer a million  men in battlefield, yet he, indeed, is the noblest victor who has conquered himself.</par>
      <summary>Self-conquest is the best of all conquests</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="104">Self-conquest  is, indeed, far greater than the conquest of all other folk; neither a god nor a gandhabba,  nor Mara  with Brahma,  can win back the victory of such a person who is self-subdued and ever lives in restraint.</par>
      <par nr="105">Self-conquest  is, indeed, far greater than the conquest of all other folk; neither a god nor a gandhabba,  nor Mara  with Brahma,  can win back the victory of such a person who is self-subdued and ever lives in restraint.</par>
      <summary>None can turn into defeat self-victory</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="106">Though month after month with a thousand, one should make an offering for a hundred years, yet, if, only for a moment, one should honour (a Saint) who has perfected himself - that honour is, indeed, better than a century of sacrifice.</par>
      <summary>A moment's honour to the worthy is better than long continued honour to the unworthy</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="107">Though, for a century a man should tend the (sacred) fire in the forest, yet, if, only for a moment, he should honour (a Saint) who has perfected himself - that honour is, indeed, better than a century of fire-sacrifice.</par>
      <summary>A moment's honour to the pure is better than a century of fire-sacrifice</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="108">In this world whatever gift  or alms a person seeking merit should offer for a year, all that is not worth a single quarter of the reverence towards the Upright  which is excellent.</par>
      <summary>Better than sacrificial slaughter of animals is honour to the pure ones</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="109">For one who is in the habit of constantly honouring and respecting the elders, four blessings increase - age, beauty, bliss, and strength.</par>
      <summary>Blessed indeed are they who honour those worthy of honour</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="110">Though one should live a hundred years, immoral and uncontrolled, yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who is moral and meditative.</par>
      <summary>A short but virtuous life is better than a long but immoral life</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="111">Though one should live a hundred years without wisdom and control, yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who is wise and meditative.</par>
      <summary>A brief life of wisdom is better than a long life of stupidity</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="112">Though one should live a hundred years idle and inactive yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who makes an intense effort.</par>
      <summary>A brief life of reflection is better than a long life of non-reflection</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="113">Though one should live a hundred years without comprehending how all things rise and pass away,  yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who comprehends how all things rise and pass away.</par>
      <summary>One day of experiencing the deathless is better than a century without such an experience</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="114">Though one should live a hundred years without seeing the Deathless State,  yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who sees the Deathless State.</par>
      <summary>One day of perceiving the deathless is better than a century without such an experience</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="115">Though one should live a hundred years not seeing the Truth Sublime,  yet better, indeed, is a single day's life of one who sees the Truth Sublime.</par>
      <summary>One day of perceiving the dhamma is better than a century without such perception</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="9">
    <title pali="Pāpa Vagga" en="Evil" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="116">Make haste in doing good;  check your mind from evil;  for the mind of him who is slow in doing meritorious actions  delights in evil.</par>
      <summary>Be quick in doing good; suppress evil</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="117">Should a person commit evil, he should not do it again and again; he should not find pleasure therein: painful is the accumulation of evil.</par>
      <summary>Do no evil again and again</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="118">Should a person perform a meritorious action, he should do it again and again; he should find pleasure therein: blissful is the accumulation of merit.</par>
      <summary>Do good again and again</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="119">Even an evil-doer sees good as long as evil ripens not; but when it bears fruit, then he sees the evil results. </par>
      <par nr="120">Even a good person sees evil so long as good ripens not; but when it bears fruit then the good one sees the good results. </par>
      <summary>By its effects evil is known</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="121">Do not disregard evil, saying, "It will not come nigh unto me"; by the falling of drops even a water-jar is filled; likewise the fool, gathering little by little, fills himself with evil.</par>
      <summary>Think not lightly of evil</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="122">Do not disregard merit, saying "It will not come nigh unto me"; by the falling of drops even a water-jar is filled; likewise the wise man, gathering little by little, fills himself with good.</par>
      <summary>Think not lightly of good</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="123">Just as a merchant, with a small escort and great wealth, avoids a perilous route, just as one desiring to live avoids poison, even so should one shun evil things.</par>
      <summary>Shun evil like a perilous path</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="124">If no wound there be in one's hand, one may carry poison in it. Poison does not affect one who has no wound. There is no ill for him who does no wrong. </par>
      <summary>No evil to those who have no bad intention</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="125">Whoever harms a harmless person, one pure and guiltless, upon that very fool the evil recoils like fine dust thrown against the wind.</par>
      <summary>Who harms the innocent comes to grief</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="126">Some are born  in a womb; evil-doers (are born) in woeful states;  the well-conducted go to blissful states;  the Undefiled Ones  pass away into Nibbāna.</par>
      <summary>Birth depends on actions</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="127">Not in the sky, nor in mid-ocean, nor in a mountain cave, is found that place on earth where abiding one may escape from (the consequences) of one's evil deed. </par>
      <summary>Nobody is exempt from the effects of evil kamma</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="128">Not in the sky, nor in mid-ocean, nor in a mountain cave, is found that place on earth where abiding one will not be overcome by death.</par>
      <summary>Death cannot be overcome</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="10">
    <title pali="Daṇóa Vagga" en="The Rod Or Punishment" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="129">All tremble at the rod. All fear death. Comparing others with oneself, one should neither strike nor cause to strike. </par>
      <summary>Kill not</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="130">All tremble at the rod. Life is dear to all. Comparing others with oneself, one should neither strike nor cause to strike.</par>
      <summary>Life is dear to all</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="131">Whoever, seeking his own happiness, harms with the rod other pleasure-loving beings experiences no happiness hereafter.</par>
      <par nr="132">Whoever, seeking his own happiness, harms not with the rod other pleasure-loving beings, experiences happiness hereafter.</par>
      <summary>Molest none</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="133">Speak not harshly to anyone. Those thus addressed will retort. Painful, indeed, is vindictive speech. Blows in exchange may bruise you.</par>
      <par nr="134">If, like a cracked gong, you silence yourself, you have already attained Nibbāna:  no vindictiveness will be found in you.</par>
      <summary>Speak not harshly</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="135">As with a staff the herdsmen  drives his kine  to pasture,  even so do old age and death drive out the lives of beings.</par>
      <summary>Decay and death are universal</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="136">So, when a fool does wrong deeds, he does not realize (their evil nature); by his own deeds the stupid man is tormented, like one burnt by fire.</par>
      <summary>The evil-doer is consumed by the effect of his own evil</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="137">He who with the rod harms the rodless and harmless,  soon will come to one of these states:-</par>
      <par nr="138">He will be subject to acute pain,  disaster, bodily injury, or even grievous sickness, or loss of mind, or oppression by the king, or heavy accusation, or loss of relatives, or destruction of wealth,  or ravaging fire that will burn his house. Upon the dissolution of the body such unwise man will be born in hell.</par>
      <par nr="139">He will be subject to acute pain,  disaster, bodily injury, or even grievous sickness, or loss of mind, or oppression by the king, or heavy accusation, or loss of relatives, or destruction of wealth,  or ravaging fire that will burn his house. Upon the dissolution of the body such unwise man will be born in hell.</par>
      <par nr="140">He will be subject to acute pain,  disaster, bodily injury, or even grievous sickness, or loss of mind, or oppression by the king, or heavy accusation, or loss of relatives, or destruction of wealth,  or ravaging fire that will burn his house. Upon the dissolution of the body such unwise man will be born in hell.</par>
      <summary>He who offends the innocent comes to grief</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="141">Not wandering naked,  nor matted locks,  nor filth,  nor fasting,  nor lying on the ground,  nor dust,  nor ashes,  nor striving squatting on the heels,  can purify a mortal who has not overcome doubts. </par>
      <summary>External penances cannot purify a person</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="142">Though gaily decked, if he should live in peace, (with passions) subdued, (and senses) controlled, certain  (of the four Paths of Sainthood), perfectly pure,  laying aside the rod (in his relations) towards all living beings,  a Brāhmaṇa  indeed is he, an ascetic  is he, a bhikkhu  is he. </par>
      <summary>Not by external appearance does one become holy</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="143">(Rarely) is found in this world anyone who, restrained by modesty, avoids reproach, as a thorough-bred horse (avoids) the whip. </par>
      <par nr="144">Like a thorough-bred horse touched by the whip, even so be strenuous and zealous. By confidence, by virtue, by effort, by concentration, by investigation of the Truth, by being endowed with knowledge and conduct,  and by being mindful, get rid of this great suffering.</par>
      <summary>The modest are rare in this world</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="145">Irrigators lead the waters. Fletchers bend the shafts. Carpenters bend the wood. The virtuous control themselves. </par>
      <summary>The good control themselves</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="11">
    <title pali="Jarā Vagga" en="Old Age" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="146">What is laughter, what is joy, when the world is ever burning?  Shrouded by darkness, would you not seek the light?</par>
      <summary>Seek the light</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="147">Behold this beautiful body, a mass of sores, a heaped-up (lump), diseased, much thought of, in which nothing lasts, nothing persists. </par>
      <summary>Foul is this gaily decked body</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="148">Thoroughly worn out is this body, a nest of diseases, perishable. This putrid mass breaks up. Truly, life ends in death.</par>
      <summary>Life ends in death</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="149">Like gourds cast away in autumn are these dove-hued bones. What pleasure is there in looking at them?</par>
      <summary>What delight in seeing white bones?</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="150">Of bones is (this) city made, plastered with flesh and blood. Herein are stored decay, death, conceit, and detraction.</par>
      <summary>This body is composed of flesh and blood</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="151">Even ornamented royal chariots wear out. So too the body reaches old age. But the Dhamma  of the Good grows not old. Thus do the Good reveal it among the Good. </par>
      <summary>Righteousness does not wear away</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="152">The man of little learning grows old like the ox. His muscles grow; his wisdom grows not.</par>
      <summary>One with little learning lacks wisdom</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="153">Through many a birth I wandered in sa��sāra,  seeking, but not finding, the builder of the house. Sorrowful is it to be born again and again.</par>
      <par nr="154">O house-builder! Thou art seen. Thou shalt build no house again. All thy rafters are broken. Thy ridge-pole is shattered. My mind has attained the unconditioned. Achieved is the end of craving.</par>
      <summary>Craving is the builder of this house</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="155">They who have not led the Holy Life, who in youth have not acquired wealth, pine away like old herons at a pond without fish.</par>
      <par nr="156">They who have not led the Holy Life; who in youth have not acquired wealth, lie like worn-out bows, sighing after the past.</par>
      <summary>They repent who do not progress materially and spiritually</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="12">
    <title pali="Atta Vagga" en="The Self" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="157">If one holds oneself  dear, one should protect oneself well. During every one of the three watches the wise man should keep vigil.</par>
      <summary>Be vigilant</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="158">Let one first establish oneself in what is proper, and then instruct others. Such a wise man will not be defiled. </par>
      <summary>Advisers should set the example first</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="159">As he instructs others so should he himself act. Himself fully controlled, he should control (others); for oneself, indeed, is difficult to control.</par>
      <summary>Act as you instruct</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="160">Oneself, indeed, is one's saviour, for what other saviour would there be? With oneself well controlled one obtains a saviour difficult to find.</par>
      <summary>Self is one's refuge</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="161">By oneself alone is evil done; it is self-born, it is self-caused. Evil grinds the unwise as a diamond grinds a hard gem.</par>
      <summary>One is responsible for one's evil</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="162">He who is exceedingly corrupt, like a māluvā creeper strangling a sal tree, does to himself what even an enemy would wish for him.</par>
      <summary>The corrupt bring about their own ruin</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="163">Easy to do are things that are hard and not beneficial to oneself, but very, very, difficult indeed, to do is that which is beneficial and good.</par>
      <summary>Evil is easy but good is difficult</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="164">The stupid man, who, on account of false views, scorns the teaching of the Arahants, the Noble Ones, and the Righteous, ripens like the fruit of the kāshta reed, only for his own destruction.</par>
      <summary>Scorn not the noble</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="165">By oneself, indeed, is evil done; by oneself is one defiled. By oneself is evil left undone; by oneself indeed, is one purified. Purity and impurity depend on oneself. No one purifies another.</par>
      <summary>Purity and impurity depend on oneself</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="166">For the sake of others' welfare, however great, let not one neglect one's own welfare.  Clearly perceiving one's own welfare, let one be intent on one's own goal.</par>
      <summary>Strive for your spiritual welfare</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="13">
    <title pali="Loka Vagga" en="The World" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="167">Do not serve mean ends,  Do not live in heedlessness. Do not embrace false views. Do not be a world-upholder. </par>
      <summary>Give up base desires</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="168">Be not heedless in standing  (at people's doors for alms). Observe (this) practice scrupulously. He who observes this practice lives happily both in this world and in the next.</par>
      <par nr="169">Scrupulously observe (this) practice. Do not observe it unscrupulously. He who observes this practice lives happily both in this world and in the next.</par>
      <summary>The righteous are happy be righteous</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="170">Just as one would look upon a bubble, just as one would look upon a mirage  - if a person thus looks upon the world, the King of Death sees him not.</par>
      <summary>Like a bubble is this world</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="171">Come, behold this world  which is like unto an ornamented royal chariot, wherein fools flounder, but for the wise there is no attachment.</par>
      <summary>The wise are not attached to the world</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="172">Whoever was heedless before and afterwards is not; such a one illumines this world like the moon freed from clouds.</par>
      <summary>The heedful illumine the world</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="173">Whoever, by a good deed,  covers the evil done,  such a one illumines this world like the moon freed from clouds.</par>
      <summary>Evil can be erased by good</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="174">Blind is this world. Few are those who clearly see. As birds escape from a net few go to a blissful state. </par>
      <summary>Few are the clear-sighted</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="175">Swans wing along on the path of the sun. (Men) go through air by psychic powers,  The wise are led away from the world,  having conquered Māra and his host. </par>
      <summary>The wise seek an escape from this world</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="176">There is no evil that cannot be done by the liar,  who has transgressed the one law (of truthfulness) and who is indifferent to a world beyond.</par>
      <summary>There is no evil that a liar cannot commit</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="177">Verily misers go not to the celestial realms. Fools do not indeed praise liberality. The wise man rejoices in giving and thereby become happy thereafter.</par>
      <summary>The stingy are not happy</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="178">Better than absolute sovereignty  over the earth, better than going to heaven, better than even lordship over all the worlds, is the Fruit of a Stream-Winner. </par>
      <summary>Spiritual advancement is better than worldly sovereignty</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="14">
    <title pali="Buddha Vagga" en="The Buddha" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="179">Whose conquest (of passion) is not turned into defeat,  no conquered (passion) of his in this world follows him  - that trackless  Buddha of infinite range,  by which way will you lead him?</par>
      <par nr="180">Him in whom there is not that entangling,  embroiling craving to lead (to any life), him the trackless Buddha of infinite range - by which way will you lead him? </par>
      <summary>The buddha cannot be fathomed</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="181">The wise ones who are intent on meditation,  who delight in the peace of renunciation  (i.e., Nibbāna), such mindful perfect Buddhas even the gods hold (most) dear.</par>
      <summary>Buddhas are dear to all</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="182">Rare is birth as a human being. Hard is the life of mortals. Hard is the hearing of the Sublime Truth. Rare is the appearance of the Buddhas.</par>
      <summary>The good are rare</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="183">Not to do any evil,  to cultivate good, to purify one's mind, this is the Teaching of the Buddhas. </par>
      <par nr="184">Forbearing patience is the highest austerity. Nibbāna is supreme, say the Buddhas. He, verily, is not a recluse  who harms another. Nor is he an ascetic  who oppresses others.</par>
      <par nr="185">Not insulting, not harming, restraint according to the Fundamental Moral Code,  moderation in food, secluded abode, intent on higher thoughts,  - this is the Teaching of the Buddhas.</par>
      <summary>Do good and be good</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="186">Not by a shower of gold coins does contentment arise in sensual pleasures. Of little sweetness, and painful, are sensual pleasures. Knowing thus, the wise man finds no delight even in heavenly pleasures. The disciple of the Fully Enlightened One delights in the destruction of craving.</par>
      <par nr="187">Not by a shower of gold coins does contentment arise in sensual pleasures. Of little sweetness, and painful, are sensual pleasures. Knowing thus, the wise man finds no delight even in heavenly pleasures. The disciple of the Fully Enlightened One delights in the destruction of craving.</par>
      <summary>Insatiate are sensual pleasures</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="188">To many a refuge fear-stricken men betake themselves - to hills, woods, groves, trees, and shrines.</par>
      <par nr="189">Nay no such refuge is safe, no such refuge is supreme. Not by resorting to such a refuge is one freed from all ill.</par>
      <par nr="190">He who has gone for refuge to the Buddha, the Dhamma, and the Sangha, sees with right knowledge the four Noble Truths - Sorrow, the Cause of Sorrow, the Transcending of Sorrow, and the Noble Eightfold Path which leads to the Cessation of Sorrow. This, indeed, is refuge secure. This, indeed, is refuge supreme. By seeking such refuge one is released from all sorrow.</par>
      <par nr="191">He who has gone for refuge to the Buddha, the Dhamma, and the Sangha, sees with right knowledge the four Noble Truths - Sorrow, the Cause of Sorrow, the Transcending of Sorrow, and the Noble Eightfold Path which leads to the Cessation of Sorrow. This, indeed, is refuge secure. This, indeed, is refuge supreme. By seeking such refuge one is released from all sorrow.</par>
      <par nr="192">He who has gone for refuge to the Buddha, the Dhamma, and the Sangha, sees with right knowledge the four Noble Truths - Sorrow, the Cause of Sorrow, the Transcending of Sorrow, and the Noble Eightfold Path which leads to the Cessation of Sorrow. This, indeed, is refuge secure. This, indeed, is refuge supreme. By seeking such refuge one is released from all sorrow.</par>
      <summary>Release from suffering is gained by seeking refuge in the buddha, dhamma and the sangha</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="193">Hard to find is a man of great wisdom: such a man is not born everywhere. Where such a wise man is born, that family thrives happily.</par>
      <summary>The noble are rare</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="194">Happy is the birth of Buddhas. Happy is the teaching of the sublime Dhamma. Happy is the unity of the Sangha.  Happy is the discipline of the united ones.</par>
      <summary>Things that tend to happiness</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="195">He who reverences those worthy of reverence, whether Buddhas or their disciples; those who have overcome the impediments  and have got rid of grief and lamentation - the merit of him who reverences such peaceful  and fearless Ones  cannot be measured by anyone as such and such.</par>
      <par nr="196">He who reverences those worthy of reverence, whether Buddhas or their disciples; those who have overcome the impediments  and have got rid of grief and lamentation - the merit of him who reverences such peaceful  and fearless Ones  cannot be measured by anyone as such and such.</par>
      <summary>Honour to whom honour is due</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="15">
    <title pali="Sukha Vagga" en="Happiness" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="197">Ah, happily do we live without hate amongst the hateful; amidst hateful men we dwell unhating.</par>
      <par nr="198">Ah, happily do we live in good health  amongst the ailing; amidst ailing men we dwell in good health.</par>
      <par nr="199">Ah, happily do we live without yearning (for sensual pleasures) amongst those who yearn (for them); amidst those who yearn (for them) we dwell without yearning.</par>
      <summary>Amongst the hateful be without hate</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="200">Ah, happily do we live we who have no impediments.  Feeders of joy shall we be even as the gods of the Radiant Realm.</par>
      <summary>Be without impediments</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="201">Victory breeds hatred. The defeated live in pain. Happily the peaceful live, giving up victory and defeat.</par>
      <summary>Victory breeds hatred</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="202">There is no fire like lust, no crime like hate. There is no ill like the body,  no bliss higher than Peace (Nibbāna).</par>
      <summary>Lust is a fire</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="203">Hunger  is the greatest disease. Aggregates  are the greatest ill. Knowing this as it really is, (the wise realize) Nibbāna, bliss supreme.</par>
      <summary>Hunger is the greatest affliction</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="204">Health is the highest gain. Contentment is the greatest wealth. The trusty  are the best kinsmen. Nibbāna is the highest bliss.</par>
      <summary>Health is paramount</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="205">Having tasted the flavour of seclusion and the flavour of appeasement,  free from anguish and stain becomes he, imbibing the taste of the joy of the Dhamma.</par>
      <summary>Happy is he who tastes the flavour of truth</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="206">Good is the sight of the Ariyas: their company is ever happy. Not seeing the foolish, one may ever be happy.</par>
      <par nr="207">Truly he who moves in company with fools grieves for a long time. Association with the foolish is ever painful as with a foe. Happy is association with the wise, even like meeting with kinsfolk.</par>
      <par nr="208">Therefore:-

With the intelligent, the wise,  the learned,  the enduring,  the dutiful,  and the Ariya  - with a man of such virtue and intellect should one associate, as the moon (follows) the starry path.</par>
      <summary>Associate with the wise</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="16">
    <title pali="Piya Vagga" en="Affection" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="209">Applying oneself  to that which should be avoided, not applying oneself to that which should be pursued,  and giving up the quest,  one who goes after pleasure envies them who exert themselves. </par>
      <par nr="210">Consort not with those that are dear,  never with those that are not dear; not seeing those that are dear and seeing those that are not dear, are both painful. </par>
      <par nr="211">Hence hold nothing dear, for separation from those that are dear is bad; bonds do not exist or those to whom naught is dear or not dear.</par>
      <summary>Avoid that which should be shunned</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="212">From endearment springs grief, from endearment springs fear; for him who is wholly free from endearment there is no grief, much less fear.</par>
      <summary>Grief springs from what is dear</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="213">From affection springs grief, from affection springs fear; for him who is wholly free from affection there is no grief, much less fear.</par>
      <summary>Grief springs from affection</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="214">From attachment springs grief, from attachment springs fear; for him who is wholly free from attachment there is no grief, much less fear.</par>
      <summary>Grief springs from attachment</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="215">From lust springs grief, from lust springs fear; for him who is wholly free from lust there is no grief, much less fear.</par>
      <summary>Grief springs from lust</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="216">From craving springs grief, from craving springs fear; for him who is wholly free from craving there is no grief, much less fear.</par>
      <summary>Grief springs from craving</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="217">Whoso is perfect in virtue,  and insight,  is established in the Dhamma,  has realized the Truths,  and fulfils his own duties  - him do folk hold dear.</par>
      <summary>The virtuous are dear to all</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="218">He who has developed a wish for the Undeclared  (Nibbāna), he whose mind is thrilled (with the three Fruits ), he whose mind is not bound by material pleasures, such a person is called an "Upstream-bound One". </par>
      <summary>The non-attached go upstream</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="219">A man long absent and returned safe from afar, his kinsmen, friends, and well-wishers welcome on his arrival.</par>
      <par nr="220">Likewise, his good deeds will receive the well-doer who has gone from this world to the next, as kinsmen will receive a dear one on his return.</par>
      <summary>Merit welcomes the doers of good</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="17">
    <title pali="Kodha Vagga" en="Anger" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="221">One should give up anger. One should abandon pride. One should overcome all fetters. Ills never befall him who clings not to mind and body and is passionless.</par>
      <summary>Give up anger</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="222">Whoso checks his uprisen anger as though it were a rolling chariot, him I call a true charioteer. Other charioteers are mere rein-holders.</par>
      <summary>Control your anger</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="223">Conquer anger by love. Conquer evil by good. Conquer the stingy by giving. Conquer the liar by truth.</par>
      <summary>Overcome anger by love</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="224">One should utter the truth. One should not be angry. One should give even from a scanty store to him who asks. Along these three paths one may go to the presence of the gods.</par>
      <summary>Be truthful, patient and generous</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="225">Those sages who are harmless, and are ever restrained in body,  go to the deathless state (Nibbāna), whither gone they never grieve.</par>
      <summary>The harmless attain the deathless</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="226">The defilements  of those who are ever vigilant, who discipline themselves day and night, who are wholly intent on Nibbāna, are destroyed.</par>
      <summary>The ever vigilant give up defilements</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="227">This, O Atula,  is an old saying; it is not one of today only: they blame those who sit silent, they blame those who speak too much. Those speaking little too they blame. There is no one who is not blamed in this world.</par>
      <par nr="228">There never was, there never will be, nor does there exist now, a person who is wholly blamed or wholly praised.</par>
      <par nr="229">Examining day by day, the wise praise him who is of flawless life, intelligent, endowed with knowledge and virtue.</par>
      <par nr="230">Who deigns to blame him who is like a piece of refined gold? Even the gods praise him; by Brahma too he is praised.</par>
      <summary>There is none who is blameless in this world</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="231">One should guard against misdeeds (caused by) the body, and one should be restrained in body. Giving up evil conduct in body, one should be of good bodily conduct.</par>
      <par nr="232">One should guard against misdeeds (caused by) speech, and one should be restrained in speech. Giving up evil conduct in speech, one should be of good conduct in speech.</par>
      <par nr="233">One should guard against misdeeds (caused by) the mind, and one should be restrained in mind. Giving up evil conduct in mind, one should be of good conduct in mind.</par>
      <par nr="234">The wise are restrained in deed; in speech, too, they are restrained. The wise, restrained in mind, are indeed those who are perfectly restrained.</par>
      <summary>Be pure in deed, word and thought</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="18">
    <title pali="Mala Vagga" en="Impurities Or Taints" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="235">Like a withered leaf are you now. The messengers of death wait on you. On the threshold of decay you stand. Provision too there is none for you.</par>
      <par nr="236">Make an island unto yourself. Strive quickly; become wise. Purged of stain and passionless, you shall enter the heavenly stage of the Ariyas. </par>
      <par nr="237">Your life has come to an end now. To the presence of death you are setting out. No halting place is there for you by the way. Provision too there is none for you.</par>
      <par nr="238">Make an island unto yourself. Strive without delay; become wise. Purged of stain and passionless, you will not come again to birth and old age.</par>
      <summary>Death is near to you</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="239">By degrees, little by little, from time to time, a wise person should remove his own impurities, as a smith removes (the dross) of silver.</par>
      <summary>Purify yourself gradually</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="240">As rust sprung from iron eats itself away when arisen, even so his own deeds lead the transgressor  to states of woe.</par>
      <summary>One's evil ruins oneself</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="241">Non-recitation is the rust of incantations;  non-exertion is the rust of homes;  sloth is the taint of beauty; carelessness is the flaw of a watcher.</par>
      <summary>Causes of stain</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="242">Misconduct is the taint of a woman. Stinginess is the taint of a donor. Taints, indeed, are all evil things both in this world and in the next.</par>
      <par nr="243">A worse taint than these is ignorance, the greatest taint. Abandoning this taint, be taintless, O Bhikkhus!</par>
      <summary>Taints are evil things ignorance is the greatest taint</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="244">Easy is the life of a shameless one who is as impudent as a crow, back-biting, presumptuous, arrogant, and corrupt.</par>
      <par nr="245">Hard is the life of a modest one who ever seeks purity, is detached, humble, clean in life, and reflective.</par>
      <summary>It is easy to lead a shameless life it is hard to lead a modest life</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="246">Whoso in this world destroys life, tells lies, takes what is not given, goes to others' wives, and is addicted to intoxicating drinks, such a one digs up his own root in this world.</par>
      <par nr="247">Whoso in this world destroys life, tells lies, takes what is not given, goes to others' wives, and is addicted to intoxicating drinks, such a one digs up his own root in this world.</par>
      <par nr="248">Know thus O good man: "Not easy of restraint are evil things". Let not greed and wickedness  drag you to protracted misery.</par>
      <summary>He who does not observe the five precepts ruins himself</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="249">People give according to their faith and as they are pleased. Whoever therein is envious of others' food and drink, gains no peace  either by day or by night.</par>
      <par nr="250">But he who has this (feeling) fully cut off, uprooted and destroyed, gains peace by day and by night.</par>
      <summary>The envious are not at peace the unenvious are at peace</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="251">There is no fire like lust, no grip like hate, no net like delusion, no river like craving.</par>
      <summary>There is no river like craving</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="252">Easily seen are others' faults, hard indeed to see are one's own. Like chaff one winnows others' faults, but one's own (faults) one hides, as a crafty fowler conceals himself  by camouflage. </par>
      <summary>Easy to see are others' faults</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="253">He who sees others' faults, and is ever irritable - the corruptions of such a one grow. He is far from the destruction of corruptions. </par>
      <summary>Defilements multiply in those who seek others' faults</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="254">In the sky there is no track. Outside  there is no Saint.  Mankind delights in obstacles.  The Tathāgatas  are free from obstacles.</par>
      <par nr="255">In the sky there is no track. Outside there is no Saint. There are no conditioned things  that are eternal. There is no instability  in the Buddhas.</par>
      <summary>There are no aggregates which are eternal</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="19">
    <title pali="Dhammaññha Vagga" en="The Just Or Righteous" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="256">He is not thereby just because he hastily arbitrates cases. The wise man should investigate both right and wrong.</par>
      <par nr="257">The intelligent person who leads others not falsely but lawfully and impartially, who is a guardian of the law, is called one who abides by the law (dhammaññha).</par>
      <summary>The impartial are called the true justices</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="258">One is not thereby a learned man merely because one speaks much. He who is secure, without hate, and fearless is called "learned".</par>
      <summary>One is not deemed wise because one is garrulous</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="259">One is not versed in the Dhamma merely because one speaks too much. He who hears little and sees the Dhamma mentally,  and who does not neglect the Dhamma, is, indeed, versed in the Dhamma.</par>
      <summary>Garrulousness is not a characteristic of one who knows the dhamma</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="260">He is not thereby an elder (thera ) merely because his head is grey. Ripe is he in age. "Old-in-vain" is he called.</par>
      <par nr="261">In whom are truth,  virtue,  harmlessness, restraint  and control, that wise man who is purged of impurities,  is, indeed, called an elder.</par>
      <summary>He is a thera who is stainless</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="262">Not by mere eloquence, nor by handsome appearance, does a man become good-natured, should he be jealous, selfish, and deceitful.</par>
      <par nr="263">But in whom these are wholly cut off, uprooted and extinct, that wise man who is purged of hatred, is, indeed, called good-natured.</par>
      <summary>Not by handsome appearance does one become good-natured</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="264">Not by a shaven head does an undisciplined man,  who utters lies, become a monk. How will one who is full of desire and greed be a monk?</par>
      <par nr="265">He who wholly subdues evil deeds both small and great is called a monk because he has overcome all evil.</par>
      <summary>A shaven head does not make one a monk</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="266">He is not thereby a bhikkhu  merely because he begs from others; by following the whole code (of morality ) one certainly becomes a bhikkhu and not (merely) by such begging.</par>
      <par nr="267">Herein he who has transcended both good and evil, whose conduct is sublime, who lives with understanding in this world, he, indeed, is called a bhikkhu.</par>
      <summary>One does not become a bhikkhu merely by begging</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="268">Not by silence (alone) does he who is dull and ignorant become a sage; but that wise man who, as if holding a pair of scales, embraces the best  and shuns evil, is indeed a sage.</par>
      <par nr="269">For that reason  he is a sage. He who understands, both worlds  is, therefore, called a sage.</par>
      <summary>Silence alone does not make a sage</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="270">He is not therefore an Ariya (Noble) in that he harms living beings; through his harmlessness towards all living beings is he called an Ariya (Noble).</par>
      <summary>By harmlessness one becomes a noble (ariya)</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="271">Not only by mere morality and austerities,  nor again by much learning,  nor even by developing mental concentration, nor by secluded lodging, (thinking) "I enjoy the bliss of renunciation not resorted to by the worldling"  (not with these) should you, O bhikkhu, rest content  without reaching the extinction of the corruptions. </par>
      <par nr="272">Not only by mere morality and austerities,  nor again by much learning,  nor even by developing mental concentration, nor by secluded lodging, (thinking) "I enjoy the bliss of renunciation not resorted to by the worldling"  (not with these) should you, O bhikkhu, rest content  without reaching the extinction of the corruptions. </par>
      <summary>A bhikkhu should not be contented until he destroys all passions</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="20">
    <title pali="Magga Vagga" en="The Way Or The Path" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="273">The best of paths is the Eightfold Path.  The best of truths are the four Sayings.  Non-attachment  is the best of states. The best of bipeds is the Seeing One.</par>
      <par nr="274">This is the only Way. There is none other for the purity of vision. Do you follow this path. This is the bewilderment of Māra.</par>
      <par nr="275">Entering upon that path, you will make an end of pain. Having learnt the removal of thorns,  have I taught you the path.</par>
      <par nr="276">Striving should be done by yourselves;  the Tathāgatas  are only teachers. The meditative ones, who enter the way, are delivered from the bonds of Māra.</par>
      <summary>The eightfold path is the best</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="277">"Transient are all conditioned things":  when this, with wisdom, one discerns, then is one disgusted with ill;  this is the path to purity.</par>
      <summary>Transient are conditioned things</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="278">"Sorrowful are all conditioned things": when this, with wisdom, one discerns, then is one disgusted with ill; this is the path to purity.</par>
      <summary>Sorrowful are all conditioned things</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="279">"All Dhammas are without a soul":  when this, with wisdom, one discerns, then is one disgusted with ill; this is the path to purity.</par>
      <summary>Everything is soulless</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="280">The inactive idler who strives not when he should strive, who, though young and strong, is slothful, with (good) thoughts depressed,  does not by wisdom realize the Path.</par>
      <summary>The slothful do not realize the path</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="281">Watchful of speech, well restrained in mind, let him do nought unskilful through his body. Let him purify these three ways of action and win the path realized by the sages.</par>
      <summary>Purify thoughts, words and deeds</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="282">Verily, from meditation arises wisdom. Without meditation wisdom wanes. Knowing this twofold path of gain and loss, let one so conduct oneself that wisdom may increase.</par>
      <summary>Act in such a way that you increase your wisdom</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="283">Cut down the forest (of the passions ), but not real trees.  From the forest (of the passions) springs fear. Cutting down both forest  and brushwood (of the passions), be forestless,  O bhikkhus.</par>
      <par nr="284">For as long as the slightest brushwood (of the passions) of man towards women is not cut down, so long is his mind in bondage, like the milch calf to its mother-cow.</par>
      <summary>Be without attachment</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="285">Cut off your affection, as though it were an autumn lily, with the hand. Cultivate the very path of peace. Nibbāna has been expounded by the Auspicious One.</par>
      <summary>Develop the path of peace</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="286">Here will I live in the rainy season, here in the autumn and in the summer: thus muses the fool. He realizes not the danger (of death).</par>
      <summary>The ignorant realize not the fear of death</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="287">The doting man with mind set on children and herds, death seizes and carries away, as a great flood (sweeps away) a slumbering village.</par>
      <summary>Death seizes the doting man</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="288">There are no sons for one's protection, neither father nor even kinsmen; for one who is overcome by death no protection is to be found among kinsmen.</par>
      <par nr="289">Realizing this fact, let the virtuous and wise person swiftly clear the way that leads to Nibbāna.</par>
      <summary>No protection from any at the moment of death</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="21">
    <title pali="Pakiṇṇaka Vagga" en="Miscellaneous" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="290">If by giving up a lesser happiness, one may behold a greater one, let the wise man give up the lesser happiness in consideration of the greater happiness.</par>
      <summary>Give up the lesser happiness for the sake of the greater</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="291">He who wishes his own happiness by causing pain to others is not released from hatred, being himself entangled in the tangles of hatred.</par>
      <summary>Not hatred for hatred</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="292">What should have been done is left undone,  what should not have been done is done.  Of those who are puffed up and heedless the corruptions increase.</par>
      <par nr="293">Those who always earnestly practise "mindfulness of the body",  who follow not what should not be done, and constantly do what should be done, of those mindful and reflective ones the corruptions come to an end.</par>
      <summary>The defilements of the conceited increase</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="294">Having slain mother  (craving) and father  (conceit) and two warrior kings (views based on eternalism and nihilism), and having destroyed a country (sense-avenues and sense-objects) together with its revenue officer  (attachment), ungrieving goes the Brāhmaṇa (Arahant).</par>
      <par nr="295">Having slain mother and father and two brahmin kings, and having destroyed the perilous path  (hindrances), ungrieving goes the Brāhmaṇa (Arahant).</par>
      <summary>Arahant goes ungrieving</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="296">Well awakened the disciples of Gotama ever arise - they who by day and night always contemplate the Buddha. </par>
      <par nr="297">Well awakened the disciples of Gotama ever arise - they who by day and night always contemplate the Dhamma. </par>
      <par nr="298">Well awakened the disciples of Gotama ever arise - they who by day and night always contemplate the Sangha. </par>
      <par nr="299">Well awakened the disciples of Gotama ever arise - they who by day and night always contemplate the body. </par>
      <par nr="300">Well awakened the disciples of Gotama ever arise - they who by day and night delight in harmlessness.</par>
      <par nr="301">Well awakened the disciples of Gotama ever arise - they who by day and night delight in meditation.</par>
      <summary>Meditate on the buddha, dhamma, sangha</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="302">Difficult is renunciation, difficult is it to delight therein. Difficult and painful is household life. Painful is association with those who are incompatible. Ill befalls a wayfarer (in sa��sāra). Therefore be not a wayfarer, be not a pursuer of ill.</par>
      <summary>Hard is renunciation</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="303">He who is full of confidence  and virtue, possessed of fame and wealth, he is honoured everywhere, in whatever land he sojourns.</par>
      <summary>The devout are respected everywhere</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="304">Even from afar like the Himalaya mountain the good reveal themselves. The wicked, though near, are invisible like arrows shot by night.</par>
      <summary>The good can be seen though from afar</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="305">He who sits alone, rests alone, walks alone, unindolent, who in solitude controls himself, will find delight in the forest.</par>
      <summary>Alone one delights in solitude</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="22">
    <title pali="Niraya Vagga" en="Woeful State" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="306">The speaker of untruth goes to a woeful state, and also he who, having done aught, says, "I did not". Both after death become equal, men of base actions in the other world.</par>
      <summary>Liars suffer</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="307">Many with a yellow robe on their necks are of evil disposition and uncontrolled. Evil-doers on account of their evil deeds are born in a woeful state.</par>
      <summary>Corrupt monks suffer</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="308">Better to swallow a red-hot iron ball (which would consume one) like a flame of fire, than to be an immoral and uncontrolled person feeding on the alms offered by people.</par>
      <summary>Be not immoral</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="309">Four misfortunes befall a careless man who commits adultery: acquisition of demerit, disturbed sleep, thirdly blame, and fourthly a state of woe.</par>
      <par nr="310">There is acquisition of demerit as well as evil destiny. Brief is the joy of the frightened man and woman. The King imposes a heavy punishment. Hence no man should frequent another's wife.</par>
      <summary>Adultery is evil</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="311">Just as kusa grass, wrongly grasped, cuts the hand, even so the monkhood wrongly handled drags one to a woeful state.</par>
      <par nr="312">Any loose act, any corrupt practice, a life of dubious  holiness - none of these is of much fruit.</par>
      <par nr="313">If aught should be done, let one do it. Let one promote it steadily, for slack asceticism scatters dust all the more.</par>
      <summary>Corrupt lives entail suffering</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="314">An evil deed is better not done: a misdeed torments one hereafter. Better it is to do a good deed, after doing which one does not grieve.</par>
      <summary>Don't do even a slight wrong</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="315">Like a border city, guarded within and without, so guard yourself. Do not let slip this opportunity,  for they who let slip the opportunity grieve when born in a woeful state.</par>
      <summary>Guard yourself like a fortified city</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="316">Beings who are ashamed of what is not shameful, and are not ashamed of what is shameful, embrace wrong views and go to a woeful state.</par>
      <par nr="317">Beings who see fear in what is not to be feared, and see no fear in the fearsome, embrace false views and go to a woeful state.</par>
      <summary>Be modest where modesty is needed</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="318">Beings who imagine faults in the faultless,  and perceive no wrong in what is wrong, embrace false views and go to a woeful state.</par>
      <par nr="319">Beings knowing wrong as wrong and what is right as right, embrace right views and go to a blissful state.</par>
      <summary>See no wrong in what is not wrong</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="23">
    <title pali="Nāga Vagga" en="The Elephant" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="320">As an elephant in the battlefield withstands the arrows shot from a bow, even so will I endure abuse; verily most people are undisciplined.</par>
      <par nr="321">They lead the trained (horses or elephants) to an assembly. The king mounts the trained animal. Best among men are the trained who endure abuse.</par>
      <par nr="322">Excellent are trained mules, so are thoroughbred horses of Sindh and noble tusked elephants; but far better is he who has trained himself.</par>
      <summary>The majority are undisciplined</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="323">Surely never by those vehicles would one go to the untrodden land (Nibbāna) as does one who is controlled through his subdued  and well-trained  self.</par>
      <summary>Self-control leads to one's goal</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="324">The uncontrollable, captive tusker named Dhanapālaka, with pungent juice flowing, eats no morsel; the tusker calls to mind the elephant forest.</par>
      <summary>An elephant cared for his mother</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="325">The stupid one, when he is torpid, gluttonous, sleepy, rolls about lying like a great hog nourished on pig-wash, goes to rebirth again and again.</par>
      <summary>Be moderate in eating</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="326">Formerly this mind went wandering where it liked, as it wished and as it listed. Today with attentiveness I shall completely hold it in check, as a mahout (holds in check) an elephant in must.</par>
      <summary>Control your thoughts</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="327">Take delight in heedfulness. Guard your mind well. Draw yourselves out of the evil way as did the elephant sunk in the mire.</par>
      <summary>Avoid the evil way</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="328">If you get a prudent companion (who is fit) to live with you, who behaves well and is wise, you should live with him joyfully and mindfully, overcoming all dangers.</par>
      <par nr="329">If you do not get a prudent companion who (is fit) to live with you, who behaves well and is wise, then like a king who leaves a conquered kingdom, you should live alone as an elephant does in the elephant forest.</par>
      <par nr="330">Better it is to live alone. There is no fellowship  with the ignorant. Let one live alone doing no evil, care-free, like an elephant in the elephant forest.</par>
      <summary>Associate with the wise</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="331">When need arises, pleasant (is it to have) friends. Pleasant is it to be content with just this and that. Pleasant is merit when life is at an end. Pleasant is the shunning of all ill.</par>
      <par nr="332">Pleasant in this world is ministering to mother.  Ministering to father too is pleasant in this world. Pleasant is ministering to ascetics. Pleasant too is ministering to the Noble Ones. </par>
      <par nr="333">Pleasant is virtue (continued) until old age. Pleasant is steadfast confidence. Pleasant is the attainment of wisdom. Pleasant is it to do no evil.</par>
      <summary>Blessed are friends in need</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="24">
    <title pali="Taṇhā Vagga" en="Craving" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="334">The craving  of the person addicted to careless living grows like a creeper. He jumps from life to life like a fruit-loving monkey in the forest.</par>
      <par nr="335">Whomsoever in this world this base clinging thirst overcomes, his sorrows flourish like well-watered bãraṇa grass.</par>
      <par nr="336">Whoso in the world overcomes this base unruly craving, from him sorrows fall away like water-drops from a lotus-leaf.</par>
      <par nr="337">This I say to you: Good luck to you all who have assembled here! Dig up the root of craving like one in quest of bãraṇa's sweet root. Let not Māra  crush you again and again as a flood (crushes) a reed.</par>
      <summary>Craving arises in the negligent</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="338">Just as a tree with roots unharmed and firm, though hewn down, sprouts again, even so while latent craving is not rooted out, this sorrow springs up again and again.</par>
      <par nr="339">If in anyone the thirty-six streams (of craving ) that rush towards pleasurable thoughts  are strong, such a deluded person, torrential thoughts of lust carry off.</par>
      <par nr="340">The streams (craving) flow everywhere. The creeper (craving) sprouts  and stands.  Seeing the creeper that has sprung up, with wisdom cut off root.</par>
      <par nr="341">In beings there arise pleasures that rush (towards sense-objects) and (such beings) are steeped in craving. Bent on happiness, they seek happiness. Verily, such men come to birth and decay.</par>
      <par nr="342">Folk enwrapt in craving are terrified like a captive hare. Held fast by fetters and bonds,  for long they come to sorrow again and again.</par>
      <par nr="343">Folk, enwrapt in craving, are terrified like a captive hare. Therefore a bhikkhu who wishes his own passionlessness (Nibbāna) should discard craving.</par>
      <summary>There is suffering as long as there is craving</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="344">Whoever with no desire (for the household) finds pleasure in the forest (of asceticism) and though freed from desire (for the household), (yet) runs back to that very home. Come, behold that man! Freed, he runs back into that very bondage. </par>
      <summary>It is foolish to return to worldly life</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="345">That which is made of iron, wood or hemp, is not a strong bond, say the wise; the longing for jewels, ornaments, children, and wives is a far greater attachment.</par>
      <par nr="346">That bond is strong, say the wise. It hurls down, is supple, and is hard to loosen. This too the wise cut off, and leave the world, with no longing, renouncing sensual pleasures.</par>
      <summary>Attachment to worldly objects is far stronger than iron chains</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="347">Those who are infatuated with lust fall back into the stream as (does) a spider into the web spun by itself. This too the wise cut off and wander, with no longing, released from all sorrow.</par>
      <summary>The lustful are caught in their own web</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="348">Let go the past. Let go the future. Let go the present  (front, back and middle). Crossing to the farther shore of existence, with mind released from everything, do not again undergo birth and decay.</par>
      <summary>Release your mind</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="349">For the person who is perturbed by (evil) thoughts, who is exceedingly lustful, who contemplates pleasant things, craving increases more and more. Surely, he makes the bond (of Māra) stronger.</par>
      <par nr="350">He who delights in subduing (evil) thoughts, who meditates on "the loathesomeness"  (of the body) who is ever mindful - it is he who will make an end (of craving). He will sever Māra's bond.</par>
      <summary>Craving grows in the passionate</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="351">He who has reached the goal, is fearless, is without craving, is passionless, has cut off the thorns of life. This is his final body.</par>
      <par nr="352">He who is without craving and grasping, who is skilled in etymology and terms,  who knows the grouping of letters and their sequence - it is he who is called the bearer of the final body, one of profound wisdom, a great man.</par>
      <summary>He who is free from craving is in his final life</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="353">All have I overcome, all do I know. From all am I detached. All have I renounced. Wholly absorbed am I in "the destruction of craving".  Having comprehended all by myself, whom shall I call my teacher?</par>
      <summary>The omniscient one has no teacher</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="354">The gift of Truth excels all (other) gifts. The flavour of Truth excels all (other) flavours. The pleasure in Truth excels all (other) pleasures. He who has destroyed craving overcomes all sorrow.</par>
      <summary>The gift of truth excels all other gifts</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="355">Riches ruin the foolish, but not those in quest of the Beyond (Nibbāna). Through craving for riches the ignorant man ruins himself as (if he were ruining) others.</par>
      <summary>Riches ruin the ignorant</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="356">Weeds are the bane of fields, lust is the bane of mankind. Hence what is given to those lustless yields abundant fruit.</par>
      <par nr="357">Weeds are the bane of fields, hatred is the bane of mankind. Hence what is given to those rid of hatred yields abundant fruit.</par>
      <par nr="358">Weeds are the bane of fields, delusion is the bane of mankind. Hence what is given to those rid of delusion yields abundant fruit.</par>
      <par nr="359">Weeds are the bane of fields, craving is the bane of mankind. Hence what is given to those rid of craving yields abundant fruit.</par>
      <summary>Lust is the blemish of mankind</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="25">
    <title pali="Bhikkhu Vagga" en="The Bhikkhu Or The Mendicant" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="360">Good is restraint in the eye; good is restraint in the ear; good is restraint in the nose; good is restraint in the tongue.</par>
      <par nr="361">Good is restraint in deed; good is restraint in speech; good is restraint in mind; good is restraint in everything. The bhikkhu,  restrained at all points,  is freed from sorrow.</par>
      <summary>Guard the senses</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="362">He who is controlled in hand, in foot, in speech, and in the highest (i.e., the head); he who delights in meditation,  and is composed; he who is alone, and is contented - him they call a bhikkhu.</par>
      <summary>The fully controlled person is called a bhikkhu</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="363">The bhikkhu who is controlled in tongue, who speaks wisely,  who is not puffed up, who explains the meaning and the text - sweet, indeed, is his speech.</par>
      <summary>Sweet is his speech who controls his tongue</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="364">That bhikkhu who dwells in the Dhamma, who delights in the Dhamma, who meditates on the Dhamma, who well remembers the Dhamma, does not fall away from the sublime Dhamma.</par>
      <summary>He who finds pleasure in the dhamma does not fall</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="365">Let him not despise what he has received, nor should he live envying (the gains of) others. The bhikkhu who envies (the gains of) others does not attain concentration. </par>
      <par nr="366">Though receiving but little, if a bhikkhu does not despise his own gains, even the gods praise such a one who is pure in livelihood and is not slothful.</par>
      <summary>Be contented</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="367">He who has no thought of "l" and "mine" whatever towards mind and body, he who grieves not for that which he has not, he is, indeed, called a bhikkhu.</par>
      <summary>He is a bhikkhu who has no attachment</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="368">The bhikkhu who abides in loving-kindness,  who is pleased with the Buddha's Teaching, attains to that state of peace and happiness,  the stilling of conditioned things.</par>
      <par nr="369">Empty this boat,  O bhikkhu! Emptied by you it will move swiftly. Cutting off lust and hatred, to Nibbāna you will thereby go.</par>
      <par nr="370">Five cut off,  five give up,  five further cultivate.  The bhikkhu who has gone beyond the five bonds  is called a "Flood-Crosser".</par>
      <par nr="371">Meditate, O bhikkhu! Be not heedless. Do not let your mind whirl on sensual pleasures. Do not be careless and swallow a ball of lead. As you burn cry not "This is sorrow".</par>
      <par nr="372">There is no concentration in one who lacks wisdom, nor is there wisdom in him who lacks concentration. In whom are both concentration and wisdom, he, indeed, is in the presence of Nibbāna.</par>
      <par nr="373">The bhikkhu who has retired to a lonely abode, who has calmed his mind, who perceives the doctrine clearly, experiences a joy transcending that of men. </par>
      <par nr="374">Whenever he reflects on the rise and fall of the Aggregates, he experiences joy and happiness. To "those who know" that (reflection ) is Deathless.</par>
      <par nr="375">And this becomes the beginning here for a wise bhikkhu: sense-control, contentment, restraint with regard to the Fundamental Code (Pātimokkha ), association with beneficent and energetic friends whose livelihood is pure.</par>
      <par nr="376">Let him be cordial in his ways and refined in conduct; filled thereby with joy, he will make an end of ill.</par>
      <summary>The bhikkhu who radiates loving-kindness radiates peace</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="377">As the jasmine creeper sheds its withered flowers, even so, O bhikkhus, should you totally cast off lust and hatred.</par>
      <summary>Cast off lust and hatred</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="378">The bhikkhu who is calm in body, calm in speech, calm in mind, who is well-composed, who has spewed out worldly things, is truly called a "peaceful one".</par>
      <summary>He is peaceful who is free from all worldly things</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="379">By self do you censure yourself. By self do you examine yourself. Self-guarded and mindful, O bhikkhu, you will live happily.</par>
      <par nr="380">Self, indeed, is the protector of self. Self, indeed, is one's refuge. Control, therefore, your own self as a merchant controls a noble steed.</par>
      <summary>He who guards himself lives happily</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="381">Full of joy, full of confidence in the Buddha's Teaching, the bhikkhu will attain the Peaceful State, the stilling of conditioned things, the bliss (supreme).</par>
      <summary>With joy and faith try to win your goal</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="382">The bhikkhu who, while still young, devotes himself to the Buddha's Teaching, illumines this world like the moon freed from a cloud.</par>
      <summary>Even a young monk, if devout, can illumine the whole world</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter chapter="26">
    <title pali="Brāhmaṇa Vagga 1" en="The Brāhmaṇa" />
    <verse>
      <par nr="383">Strive and cleave the stream.  Discard, O brāhmaṇa, sense-desires. Knowing the destruction of conditioned things, be, O brāhmaṇa, a knower of the Unmade  (Nibbāna).</par>
      <summary>Be a knower of the uncreated</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="384">When in two states  a brāhmaṇa goes to the Farther Shore,  then all the fetters of that "one who knows" pass away.</par>
      <summary>Cultivate concentration and insight</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="385">For whom there exists neither the hither  nor the farther shore, nor both the hither and the farther shore,  he who is undistressed and unbound,  - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>The unbound person is a brahmana</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="386">He who is meditative,  stainless and secluded,  he who has done his duty and is free from corruptions,  he who has attained the Highest Goal  - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>He who is meditative and pure is a brahmana</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="387">The sun shines by day; the moon is radiant by night. Armoured shines the warrior king.  Meditating the brāhmaṇa  shines. But all day and night the Buddha  shines in glory.</par>
      <summary>The buddha shines throughout day and night</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="388">Because he has discarded evil, he is called a brāhmaṇa; because he lives in peace,  he is called a samana; because he gives up the impurities, he is called a pabbajita - recluse.</par>
      <summary>He is holy who has discarded all evil</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="389">One should not strike a brāhmaṇa,  nor should a brāhmaṇa vent (his wrath) on one who has struck him. Shame on him who strikes a brāhmaṇa! More shame on him who gives vent (to his wrath)!</par>
      <par nr="390">Unto a brāhmaṇa that (non-retaliation) is of no small advantage. When the mind is weaned from things dear, whenever the intent to harm ceases, then and then only doth sorrow subside.</par>
      <summary>Harm not an arahant</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="391">He that does no evil through body, speech or mind, who is restrained in these three respects - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>He is a true brahmana who is well-restrained</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="392">If from anybody one should understand the doctrine preached by the Fully Enlightened One, devoutly should one reverence him, as a brahmin reveres the sacrificial fire.</par>
      <summary>Honour to whom honour is due</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="393">Not by matted hair, nor by family, nor by birth does one become a brāhmaṇa. But in whom there exist both truth  and righteousness,  pure is he, a brāhmaṇa is he.</par>
      <summary>Pure is he who is truthful and righteous</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="394">What is the use of your matted hair, O witless man? What is the use of your antelope skin garment? Within, you are full of passions; without, you embellish yourself. </par>
      <summary>Be pure within</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="395">The person who wears dust-heap robes,  who is lean, whose veins stand out, who meditates alone in the forest - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>Who meditates alone in the forest is a brahmana</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="396">I do not call him a brāhmaṇa merely because he is born of a (brahmin) womb or sprung from a (brahmin) mother. He is merely a "Dear-addresser",  if he be with impediments. He who is free from impediments, free from clinging - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>The non-possessive and the non-attached person is a brahmana</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="397">He who has cut off all fetters, who trembles not, who has gone beyond ties, who is unbound - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has destroyed all fetters</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="398">He who has cut the strap (hatred), the thong (craving), and the rope (heresies), together with the appendages (latent tendencies), who has thrown up the cross-bar (ignorance), who is enlightened  (Buddha) - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has no hatred</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="399">He who, without anger, endures reproach, flogging and punishments, whose power and potent army is patience - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who is patient</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="400">He who is not wrathful, but is dutiful,  virtuous, free from craving, self-controlled and bears his final body,  - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who is not wrathful</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="401">Like water on a lotus leaf, like a mustard seed on the point of a needle, he who clings not to sensual pleasures - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>He is a brahmana who clings not to sensual pleasures</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="402">He who realizes here in this world the destruction of his sorrow, who has laid the burden  aside and is emancipated,  - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has laid the burden aside</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="403">He whose knowledge is deep, who is wise, who is skilled in the right and wrong way,  who has reached the highest goal - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has reached his ultimate goal</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="404">He who is not intimate either with householders or with the homeless ones, who wanders without an abode, who is without desires - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has no intimacy with any</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="405">He who has laid aside the cudgel in his dealings with beings,  whether feeble or strong, who neither harms nor kills - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who is absolutely harmless</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="406">He who is friendly amongst the hostile, who is peaceful amongst the violent, who is unattached amongst the attached,  - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who is friendly amongst the hostile</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="407">In whom lust, hatred, pride, detraction are fallen off like a mustard seed from the point of a needle - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has discarded all passions</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="408">He who utters gentle, instructive, true words, who by his speech gives offence to none - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who gives offence to none</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="409">He who in this world takes nothing that is not given, be it long or short, small or great, fair or foul - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who steals not</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="410">He who has no longings, pertaining to this world or to the next, who is desireless and emancipated - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who is desireless</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="411">He who has no longings, who, through knowledge, is free from doubts, who has gained a firm footing in the Deathless (Nibbāna) - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has no longings</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="412">Herein he who has transcended both good and bad and the ties  as well, who is sorrowless, stainless, and pure - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has transcended good and evil</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="413">He who is spotless as the moon, who is pure, serene, and unperturbed,  who has destroyed craving for becoming - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who is pure</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="414">He who has passed beyond this quagmire,  this difficult path,  the ocean of life (sa��sāra), and delusion,  who has crossed  and gone beyond, who is meditative, free from craving and doubts, who, clinging to naught, has attained Nibbāna - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who clings to naught</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="415">He who in this world giving up sense-desires, would renounce worldly life and become a homeless one, he who has destroyed sense-desires and becoming - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has given up sense-desires</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="416">He who in this world giving up craving, would renounce worldly life and become a homeless one, he who has destroyed craving and becoming - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has given up craving</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="417">He who, discarding human ties and transcending celestial ties, is completely delivered from all ties - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has discarded all bonds</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="418">He who has given up likes  and dislikes,  who is cooled and is without defilements,  who has conquered the world  and is strenuous - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has given up likes and dislikes</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="419">He who in every way knows the death and rebirth of beings, who is non-attached, well-gone,  and enlightened,  - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <par nr="420">He whose destiny neither gods nor gandhabbas  nor men know, who has destroyed all corruptions, and is far removed from passions (Arahant) - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who is not attached</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="421">He who has no clinging to Aggregates that are past, future, or present, who is without clinging and grasping - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who yearns for naught</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="422">The fearless,  the noble, the hero, the great sage,  the conqueror,  the desireless, the cleanser  (of defilements), the enlightened,  - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who is enlightened</summary>
    </verse>
    <verse>
      <par nr="423">That sage who knows his former abodes, who sees the blissful  and the woeful states,  who has reached the end of births,  who, with superior wisdom, has perfected himself,  who has completed  (the holy life), and reached the end of all passions - him I call a brāhmaṇa.</par>
      <summary>A brahmana is he who has perfected himself</summary>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</dhammapada>